Guide to the Pier A Construction Records Collection 1884-1998 PR 421
New-York Historical Society
Pier A construction records collection
1884-1998
New-York Historical Society
Wings Point Associates (East Hampton, N.Y.)
New York (N.Y.). Department of Docks (1870-1897)
New York (N.Y.). Department of Docks and Ferries
PR 421
15.5 Linear feet in 5 boxes of rolled drawings and 1 document box
Pier A is a New York City landmark, found at the south end of Manhattan at Battery Park. It was built in 1884-1886, and housed the Harbor Patrol of the New York City's Police Department and the administrative offices of the Department of Docks into the 1950s, when the Marine Administrative Unit of the Fire Department moved in. The collection primarily includes about 90 original drawings of Pier A's 1880s construction and later additions and alterations into the early 20th century. It also includes an album of historic photographs, snapshots of the demolition and construction work started in 1997-98, and research reports done for 1990s developer Wings Point Associates, the compilers of this documentation.
Arrangement
The collection is roughly organized by document format.
Biographical / Historical
Pier A extends from the Battery at the southern rim of New York City's Manhattan Island into the lower Hudson River (or North River as many of the documents in the collection refer to it) toward Ellis Island and the Statue of Liberty. It was built by the city's Department of Docks, under the leadership of Chief Engineer George Sears Greene, Jr., in 1884-1886. At completion, Pier A housed the Harbor Patrol of the city's Police Department and the administrative offices of the Department of Docks. These units, and their successor organizations, remained at Pier A until 1959, when they relocated, and were replaced by the Marine Administrative Unit of the Fire Department, which had been docking its fireboats there since the 1940s. Several alterations were made to the pier over time, including major additions in 1900-1904, installation of a clock in the campanile in 1919 as a World War I memorial, and other renovations through the mid-20th century.
In the late 1960s, Battery Park was slated for economic redevelopment and the related demolition of old structures. Pier A was one such structure targeted for destruction, but resistance by its tenant, the Fire Department, preservationists, and others saved the pier from destruction. It was placed on the National Register of Historic Places in 1975 and designated a city landmark in July 1977. Nevertheless, Pier A deteriorated and efforts to include it in the redevelopment of the area continued. In 1988, an agreement was signed with developer Wings Point Associates to repurpose Pier A as primarily a public space for leisure activities. The Fire Department moved out in 1992 and the renovation began in the late 1990s. In preparing for this renovation, Wings Point used original drawings and had historic research done to inform the design. It appears that it is these documents, at least some of them, that comprise the present collection. Wings Point's renovation eventually stalled and the developer gave up its lease in 2007. The Battery Park City Authority undertook the renovation, which was finally completed in 2014.
(The above note was based on the landmarks designation report, documents in the collection, and on-line articles from the New York Times and others.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Thomas Ickovic, 2021.
Scope and Contents
The collection primarily includes about 90 original drawings of Pier A's 1880s construction and later additions and alterations into the early 20th century. The container list provides some level of detail regarding the specific drawings and their subjects. The collection includes a reel of microfilm from 1977 that also includes images of original drawings; the overlap between these and the actual drawings in the collection was not determined during processing in 2021. The microfilm also includes original specifications and other documents that are not in paper form in the collection. A summary list of the documents on the microfilm is found at the very end of the reel and that summary was printed and is found in box 6.
The collection also includes historical research reports prepared for the Pier A developers, Wings Point Associates; an album of historic photographs and other images of Pier A, mostly reproductions, with a few originals; and snapshots of the demolition and construction undertaken in 1997-98.
Historic sites -- Conservation and restoration.; Piers -- Design and construction.; Piers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Architectural drawings (visual works); Microfilms.; Photographs.; Battery Park (New York, N.Y.)
- Pier A History and Restoration Analysis (2 folders), 1989 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-2)
  Scope and Contents
  3 documents: A history of the construction of Pier A in the 19th century, a "historical summary," and a "history and restoration analysis," all prepared by Lang Associates, Architects & Consultants, for developers Wings Point Associates Inc. The second folder holds copies of two of the documents.
- Album of Historic Photographs, circa 1920s-1990s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
  Album of images of Pier A from the 1890s to 1990s. The bulk are copies of photos obtained from New York Public Library, Parks Department, Museum of the City of New York, N-YHS, and elsewhere. But there is some original material, including a set of 4 sepia-toned photos that date from circa 1930 (Mayor Jimmy Walker is in some of them), a few vintage postcards, and a 1991 fact sheet about the proposed Pier A restoration.
- Photographs: Demolition & Construction, Dock & Breakwater, 1997 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
  4x6 inch color snapshots. Removed from deteriorating binder and plastic enclosures and placed in new enclosures.
- Photographs of construction site, 1997-1998 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
  8 8x10 inch color photographs, including building length elevation views of the scaffolding, attic roof supports (interior), and site views.
- Photographs: Construction, 1997? (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
  Various 4x6 inch snapshots of construction views and details.
- Workbook for Siding Replacement, 1990s? (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
  Includes images of historic drawings of details, prepared by Wings Point Associates
- Index of Existing Drawings for Pier A, 1990s (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)
- Microfilm, 1977 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
  One reel made in 1977 by Micrographics Enterprises. The bulk of the reel includes drawings ranging from the 1880s-mid 20th century; some of these drawings are in the collection, but most are not. The microfilm also includes specifications for work to be done on Pier A and its buildings, also ranging from the 1880s to mid-20th century. At the end of the reel is a summary list of the items on the microfilm; a copy of that list was printed and included in Box 6 with the microfilm reel.
- Side Wall Framing and Miscellaneous Details (1935); Alteration to Pier A; Framing Plans & Sections (undated) (2 drawings), 1935, undated (Offsite-box 1, Roll 1)
- Floor Plans (5 drawings), 1885-1922 (Offsite-box 1, Roll 1)
  Upper story plan (1885); office floor plan (1904, revised 1911, correct at 1914); 2 office floor plan (1921); deck plan (1922).
- Repairs & Extension to Building on Pier A (3 drawings), undated (Offsite-box 1, Roll 2)
  Detail of Side Balcony-Window, Tube 495, letter Y; Ash Panelled Partition, Tube 495, letter U; full size detail of galvanized iron finials, tube 495, letter T.
- Repairs & Extensions to Pier A (8 drawings), undated (Offsite-box 1, Roll 3)
  Various details of architrave, cornice, pilasters, etc. Labelled Tube 495, letters A,B,C,D,F,H; Tube 483, letter M; Tube 499, letter K.
- Repairs & Extensions to Pier A (7 drawings), undated (Offsite-box 1, Roll 4)
  Includes various details of front central portion, pediment to front entrance doors, antifixa, etc. Labelled Tube 495, letters J,K,N,T,X. Tube 499, letter H. One reproduction, modern index #H16.
- Photocopies (5 drawings), 1884-1948 (Offsite-box 2, Roll 5)
  Photocopies of originals: Cross Sections of Pier Deck, Tube 477, letter J (1884); Iron Framing for Roof of Tower, Tube 479, letter C(?), with modern index# H8 (1885); Pier A Building's elevations, Tube 476, with modern index# H2; building's main stairs, Tube 482, letter B; and north and south elevations, modern index# H18 (1948).
- Repairs & Extension to Building [Head House] on Pier A (7 drawings), 1900 March (Offsite-box 2, Roll 6)
  Labeled as Tube 494, letters B,D,F,G,I,M,R.
- Alterations on Pier A for Police Department (1 drawing), 1887 January (Offsite-box 2, Roll 7)
  Labeled as Tube 485, letter F.
- Repairs & Extension to Building on Pier A; Break Water at Pier A (3 blueprints), 1900? (Offsite-box 2, Roll 8)
  The "repairs" blueprint no longer has a label due to fragmenting; a date written on the reverse indicates August 1900. There are two blueprints concerning the breakwater: One of the overall plan blueprint, labeled as Tube 329a, letter W, but which has lost a date due to fragmenting; and a small blueprint of the breakwater's special coping stones, labeled as Tube 329a, letter P (undated).
- Various (6 documents), 1886, undated (Offsite-box 3, Roll 9)
  Includes 6 documents rolled together: 2 letters from contractors V.J. Hedden & Sons to Engineer-in-Chief Greene proposing detail work on various rooms (1886); small drawing of "general style of partition a[?] & lines of moulding, etc." labeled as Tube 485, letter D (undated); elevations of partitions for southside of commissioner's office and for west wall of 1st deputy commissioner's office (undated); blueprint of ash railing with gate for bookkeeper's room, labeled as Tube 490, letter F (undated); and blueprint of ash panelled partition for repairs & extension, though full name, tube, date are lost due to fragmenting.
- Pier A building plans (3 drawings), 1885 (Offsite-box 3, Roll 10)
  Includes 3 drawings labeled Tube 483, letters, A,E,H. one is for sheet metal work about the arches, one is balcony details, the third is unlabeled but relates to sheet metal work at windows.
- Float Stage at Pier A (7 drawings), 1895 (Offsite-box 3, Roll 11)
  Labeled as Tube 665, letters A,B,C,F,G,H,J.
- Building for Pier A, Inshore Part (13 drawings), 1885 July (Offsite-box 3, Roll 12)
  Labeled as tube 481, letters B,C,D,F,G,H,I,K,N,O,P,Q,P,R.
- Various plans (11 drawings), 1893, 1906, undated (Offsite-box 4, Roll 13)
  Includes new weathervane, Tube 483, letter Z (1893); Plan for dining room and kitchen, Tube 490, letter G; Storerooms on lower deck of Pier A, Tube 493, letter J; plans & elevations of automobile garage, Tube 496, letter D (1906); 6 drawings of repairs and alterations to the building on Pier A, Tube 499, letters B,C,D,E,F,G; Suspension rods for passageway in roof loft of fireproof portion of building, Tube 499, letter M.
- Various plans (5 drawings), 1896, 1901, undated (Offsite-box 4, Roll 14)
  Includes repairs & alterations for police station, Tube 498, letter B (1901); landing float, Tube 665, letters,D,E,I; and steam and waste pipes and heaters on Pier A, office copy (1896).
- Details of lettering and lamps (7 drawings), 1885 (Offsite-box 4, Roll 15)
  Labeled as Tube 483, letters C,U,V,W,X,Y, a(?)
- Various details (2 drawings), undated (Offsite-box 5, Roll 16)
  1 drawing of sheathing details, Tube 499, letter J, and 1 drawing of will sill and box, Tube 493(?), letter O.
- Design, Electric Work for Pier A (1 blueprint), 1930 (Offsite-box 5, Roll 17)
  Fragmented